<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle directed to all iustices of peace in England and Wales.</title>
            <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2025A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E133_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19844</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860751</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860751</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112876</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76450)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112876)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 24:E133[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle directed to all iustices of peace in England and Wales.</title>
                  <author>Bernard, Richard, 1568-1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M. S.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Warning the justices of the dangers of Catholics in England.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>A reissue, with cancel title page, of the edition dated 1641 in imprint.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "by mr Barnard of Batcome.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112876:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112876:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE DIRECTED TO ALL Iuſtices of Peace IN <hi>ENGLAND</hi> AND <hi>WALES.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>M. S.</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:112876:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112876:2"/>
            <head>TO THE VVATCHFVLL Eyes in this our ſtate, the worthy
<hi>Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> Impriſoners of Malefactors, and Preſervers of peace; that peace is wiſhed which paſſeth all underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, with the zeale of God, in due execution of Iuſtice againſt the enemies of Chriſt, and our Countrey.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat furtherance your places of Iuſtice bee to Iudges, ſitting in the ſeate of judgement, is better knowne unto your wiſedome, and learned ſelves, then I can any way immagine or think. Yet I, by my light obſervation, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive thus much, what without your vigelancy and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; the Iudges cannot doe, what either their places re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, or themſelves deſire to doe, for the good of our countrey. As therefore I have beene bold, in the zeale of God, and cauſe of Religion, humbly to petition them: ſo in like manner, I beſeech you, in your places, to doe this good for Gods Church, to ſearch out theſe walking ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Antichriſt; I meane the Prieſts and Ieſuites, that they may be conjured downe by the power of the law and ſword, which doe ſo audaciouſly riſe up, with contempt of the word and ſpirituall power of Chriſt. Likewiſe that the ſtatutes be executed upon open Recuſants, who too boldly dare to profeſſe themſelves of the Popiſh Church. And withall, that a circumſpect eye bee had of our Church-Papiſts: ſuch, as for all their open comming to our aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, <pb facs="tcp:112876:3"/>doe ſufficiently in many particulars, declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be in their comming to Church, the very meere ſervants of Men; their courſe at home, and abroad, being duely examined. And that you may ſee, what may truely, and without breach of charity, be thought of theſe, I will be bold with a godly learned friend of mine,<note place="margin">Mr. R.B.</note> to ſet downe unto you, what he concerning theſe Church-Papiſt, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered, as a preface before his Sermon once, at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe, word for word, as neere as may be. His affirmation was this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conformity to the Oath of alleagiance, and other outward formall ſatisfactions of the State, concurring wtth a reſolution to continue in Poperie, is farre more pernicious to the State, then open and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest Recuſancie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay it againe (ſaith hee), A fellow which hath taken the oath of allegiance; <hi>firſt,</hi> either by power of ſome Popiſh diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, which great men eſpecially may eaſily procure, becauſe by their wit, or worth, or high roome, they may be more notoriouſly ſerviceable to the Church of Rome; or <hi>ſecondly,</hi> by proportionable deduction of ſome warrant to their conſciences in that caſe, from that breife of <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> in the Queenes time, mentioned before, which any vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Papiſt will eaſily apprehend: or <hi>thirdly,</hi> by the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning art of mentall reſervation, of which (perhaps) ſome of their Prieſts &amp; cunninger ſort, eſpecially of the equivocal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting generation, will bee ready to make advantage of; or <hi>fourthly,</hi> by reaſon of wideneſſe of conſcience, even directly and groſly againſt the corrupt notious and inſtructions ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; which is much incident to the more ignorant and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior rancke of Papiſts, who through baſeneſſe and lowneſſe of ſtate, are exempted from inteligence with the Conſiſtorie of Rome, and acquaintance with the liberty of many popiſh reſolutions in ſuch caſes, and having no grounded and reall <pb facs="tcp:112876:3"/>aſſurance of ſalvation in that profeſſion (which is an inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable miſerie to popiſh heriſie), dare not hazard their temporall happineſſe, for any hope of future comfort they are ever like to have, or reape by ſuch a miſerable religion: I ſay, a fellow having thus taken the oath of allegiance either by popiſh diſpenſation, mentall reſervation, or directly and groſly againſt the checke and contradiction of his popi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> conſcience, is by accident, and by conſequent, farr more Peſtilentiall to the State then he was before, for ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By this formall outward falſe hearted-conformitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, he diverts and declines the watchfull eye of ſtate-rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſie, from ordinary excubation and vigilancie over his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh villanies and machinations, from a more narrow parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular inſinuation into his vnder-ground vaults, and timely obſervation of his engroſſing too much gun-power; and ſo workes a great deale of miſchiefe vnobſervedly, fearfully vndermines, without any countermine of policie; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currers moſt danderouſly with the outraged malice of that <hi>man of ſinne,</hi> for the waſting of our Church, and diſ-ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening the State, without ſence or ſuſpition.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he is vnworthily armed with the reſpect and reputation of a good ſubiect; and ſo may more boyſterouſly and with greater bravery, wound and weaken the better ſide; vexe goodneſſe, and good men, more boldly without controlment, and ſecretly promote Poperie, and hinder proceedings againſt Papiſts, even with authority, and ſome colourable oſtentations of ſafer policie, and floriſhing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of deeper reaches into the miſteries of State.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, hee may thereby give deeper wounds into the heart of the truth, through the ſides of thoſe they call Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans; and over their heads doe his worſt to knocke out the braines of the bleſſed Goſpell of the ſonne of God. It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible, <pb facs="tcp:112876:4"/>what a world of wrong and miſchieſe is wrought vpon the truth which we profeſſe, and true profeſſours thereof, by politicke conformable Papiſts, vpon the wofull advantage of certaine Miniſters inconformitie. If ſuch a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſpie out a conſionable painfull Miniſter, and finde him obnoxious to the rigour of the law, but in the leaſt point; and that (perhaps) out of a peacefull tenderneſſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, while himſelfe is in heart a ranke traitor to the State. O then he plies the advantage with much malice and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by informations, aggrapations, exaſperations fawning concurrence with Eccleſiaſticall Courts, untill hee have procured the putting out of that burning &amp; ſhining lampe, (for he well knowes, when ſuch lights expire, the noyſome ſnufe of Popery is like enough to infect that darkeſome place:) and God knowes, all this is done, not for preſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of peace, as he publikely pretends; but for promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Popery, which he ſecretly intends. I woul to God, the reverend Biſhops and Fathers of our Church, would wiſely thinke of this point, before it be too late, I ſpeake not here any thing to harden the Separatiſt, or any truly tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous; but to point out a dangerous depth of the <hi>miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of iniquitie,</hi> which worketh peſtilently upon ſuch advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages. I rather pray, that all the bleſſings of the God of peace, both in this world, and in the world to come, may be heaped upon his head, whoſoever hee bee, which doth any way (with holineſſe and good conſcience) labour to further the peace of our too much diſtracted Sion.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, he that conformes, in outward obedience, to the State, by warrant of Popiſh diſpenſation, muſt labour to recompence the Popes liberality in that kind, with ſome more remarkable and notorious ſervice to the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> Hee ſhall finde himſelfe, out of a ſenſe of ſuch extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry favour from that unholy Father, bound in conſcience, and ingaged in congruitie, to be more ready and reſolute <pb facs="tcp:112876:4"/>vpon occaſion or advantage, upon any deſperate adventure and high attempt, for the advancement of his triple infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall crowne.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, hee that with wilfull inlargement of conſcience, and ſecret ſturdie reſolution, takes the oath, will eaſily and naturally grow revengefully inraged againſt the righteous Torturers, and conformers of his corrupt and exorbitant conſcience.</p>
            <p>The conſcience receiving a ſting, transfuſeth the ſmart into the affections, Which when they feele, they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently furiouſly inraged againſt the occaſioners of that their bitter miſery. And therefore I am perſwaded, ſuch a fellow, ſo taking the Oath, howſoever he may beare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe reſervedly, is afterwards tranſported, with more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and implacable ſpite, againſt the power of that truth, and patrons of that profeſſion, (a ſacred zeale whereof hath juſtly brought a racke and vexation upon his miſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded conſcience) then he was before. And aſſuredly, if the times ſhould turne, (which God forbid) wee ſhould finde the Church-Papiſt, and the politicke conformable
<hi>Pſeudo-Catholicke,</hi> more mercileſſe &amp; blood thirſty againſt us, then the Recuſant, Though the beſt of them, no doubt, at that day, would be as a Brier, and ſharper then a thornie hedge; nay even as a woolfe in the evening. For there is no malice neere unto the malice of Popery, ſave the malice of Hell.</p>
            <p>Vpon theſe grounds alſo, I have thought, that as the ſtate of a Church-Papiſt, obſtinated in popery, is moſt damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in it ſelfe, (even the popiſh Doctours themſelves being witneſſes) as I have proved elſewhere: (ſee my book of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall repentance, p. 59.) ſo it is moſt dangerous to the State.</p>
            <p>I ſpeake not this to drive or detaine any Papiſt from the Church, for I pronounce unto him, out of the word of life <pb facs="tcp:112876:5"/>and truth, hee muſt flie out of Babylon, into Sion, if ever hee will ſave his ſoule: but to let him know, that comming to our congregation, he ought with humility, reverence, and prayer, to ſubmit his underſtanding to illumination with truth, and his heart to ſanctification with grace, both for the procurement and comfort of his owne ſalvation, and the contentment and ſafety of the State. Otherwiſe, as his dangerouſneſſe to the State is evident and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: ſo his owne damnation ſleepeth not. For, if popery were truth, as it is not, but the very doctrine of Divels; yet his State is damnable, becauſe he ſhould ſo, deny Chriſt before men: if it be falſe, as indeed it is, and moſt accurſed from heaven, then hee juſtly periſheth in his hereſie.</p>
            <p>But, it may be, ſome will here reply; what can poſſibly be more required, and exacted from theſe men, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in outward obedience to the State? what better ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, or ſurer bond, can be thought upon, then an oath, the ſacred and ſoveraigne inſtrument of all juſtice and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience amongſt men? what further invention of State, ſhall be able to ſtay the fearefull miſchiefes, that hang hourely over our heads, from this malicious and murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous generation?</p>
            <p>I anſwere, none in the world, while they ſtay amongſt us: not the moſt exquiſite and quinteſſenticall policy of all the wiſeſt States, that lie under the face of the Sunne, can affoord helpe in this caſe. I dolatry is ever attended with this inſeparable curſe, that it will plague the kingdome that nouriſheth it, and pay it home at length with a witneſſe, except ſome right round, and reſolute courſe betaken in the meane time, for the rooting of it out. And indeed the depthes of the miſtery of iniquity are ſo unfathomable, that they cannot be ſounded by the Plummet of any honeſt and Chriſtian policy, without diving into the bottome of Hell.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:112876:5"/>
            <p>It is a right juſt and holy thing, to give them the oath, and to bring them to the Church. But their violations of oathes, diſpenſations, equivocations, mentall evaſions, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of conſcience, and execrable tranſgreſſions of all lawes, both of God and man, of nations and nature, are ſo infinite and endleſſe; and they ſo mingle their concluſions of State, with the very confuſions of hell; that it is even in proportion as eaſie, to chaine up thoſe damned ſpirits, from tempting men upon earth; as to bridle thoſe blood-thirſty monſters, from undermining and overturning thoſe States; which profeſſe the truth of Chriſt, if power and meanes were anſwerable to their malice and revengefull humours.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">K. Iames</note>It was a royall providence of our gracious Soveraigne, in his firſt ſpeech in the Parliament, to admoniſh the Papiſts, that they would not ſo farre preſume upon his Lenity, as thereupon to thinke it lawfull for them, daily to increaſe their number and ſtrength in this Kingdome: whereby, if not in his time, yet leaſt in time of his poſterity, they might be in hope to erect their religion againe. But it is more then manifeſt, by daily and woefull experience, that their maine end, all their plots, practiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, ſtrange inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, &amp; the whole ſpheare of a world of Papiſt, that ſwarme amongſt us, hold a ſtrong oppoſition and counter-motion to that gratious counſell and firſt motion of his Majeſtie. A bleſſed and happie thing had it beene, had his Princely pleaſure beene followed in that point. For aſſuredly, were we rid of the Papiſts; and were Idolatry baniſhed out of the Kingdome, as in conſcience, and policie, reaſon, and religion, it ought: the King and his poſterity, by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, might ſit upon the throne of England, as faſt as the ſtrong and mighty mountaines upon their ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations. Oh, then would the forraigne mint and forge of popiſh miſchiefe, diſcontinue and expire. Ieſuites, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills <pb facs="tcp:112876:6"/>Iourneymen, would take breath, from hammering any more, their helliſh powder-plots in haſt. That malicious and murthering generation would grow diſhartened and unſpirited, for matter of project, and conſpiracie, againſt this noble State. The royall perſon of the King would have none about it, but Angels, and good ſubjects. The concurrent furie of the greateſt enemies in the world, durſt not entertaine a thought of invaſion, or ſtirre a finger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the unconquerable glory of our peace. For certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the crowne of this kingdome is incircled and ſurrounded with ſuch infinite and endleſſe variety of popiſh inſidiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and ſtands farre more liable to the furious thirſt of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne ambitions, upon this ground principally; becauſe they hope, when time ſerves, to finde amongſt us, a ſide and faction of Papiſts, to ſerve their turne. Cut the thread of this hope; and cut the throat of all plots againſt the Kings perſon; and cruſh the Popes heart, for any probability, or poſſibility of ever re-eſtabliſhing, and erecting his accurſed tyrannie, in this Iland againe.</p>
            <p>Now this bleſſed buſineſſe of moſt important and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt conſequence, for the pleaſing of God, ſecurity of the State, and preſervation of his Religion, and royall ſeed, that now fits with incomparable glory upon the Throne, would bee happily furthered.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if lawes worthily provided in ſuch caſes, might have their courſe and current, without oppoſition, diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, partiality, interception by falſe friends, or any cunning defraudations and deluſions of the holy intentions thereof.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if on our ſide there were but halfe the care and conſcience, for the maintenance of Chriſts truth, and extirpation of the infectious hereſies of the man of ſinne, which are incompatible, both with ſalvation of mens ſoules, and the ſafety of imperiall Crownes: as there is curious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <pb facs="tcp:112876:6"/>and cruelty, in Popiſh Kingdomes, for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Antichriſtianiſme; and, by a bloody inquiſition in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the very thoughts of men, (the greateſt ſlavery that ever the ſunne, or the world taſted) for the baniſhing and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out, even of all poſſibility, (ſo far as in them lies) of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, plantation of primitive truth, and profeſſion of grace.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, and above all, the plantation and protection of a conſcionable learned miniſtery, muſt doe the deed, when all is done, and ſtrike the deadlyeſt and irrevocable blow into the heart of the Pope, if the never-erring Spirit of God have told us the truth, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. The Lord will conſume the wicked man, with the ſpirit of his mouth. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, State, wiſedome, confederations of Chriſtian States, invention and execution of good lawes, the diſarming and diſabling of the Popes vaſſals, and the like are very notable and needfull meanes, glorious attendants, and aſſiſtants un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this holy worke. But the ſword of the Spirit, managed by the hand of a powerfull miniſtery, muſt ſtrike off
<hi>Holofer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> head; and knocke out the braines of the great
<hi>Goliah</hi> of Rome, which with intolerable inſolency doth revile the hoſt of the living God, and trample upon the neckes of the Lords anointed. The Champions of Chriſt, in the battell of the great day of God Almighty, at Armageddon, may beare themſelves bravely, and triumphantly: but the ſpirit of the mouth of the Lord Jeſus, ſhall carry away the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt glory of the day, in that conqueſt and confuſion of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, and in laying his triple crowne in the duſt.</p>
            <p>But in the meane time (untill the Lord put to his helping hand, for ſetting thoſe meanes on foot, with reſolution and conſtancy) it is a matter of prodigious amaſement, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how mightily impunity of popiſh idolatry provokes the wrath of God againſt us, and in what danger we ſtand; <pb facs="tcp:112876:7"/>the State, the Goſpell, the royall perſon of the King, the dayly invaluable hope of the ſucceſſion of his children, and particular welfare of every loyall ſubject in the land. For, if any man be ſo voyd of braine, to doe himſelfe and the State that wrong, as to thinke that there are not ſtill new miſchiefes on foote, and ſecret workings againſt us ſtill, by powder-plots, Pariſian Maſſacres, or ſome proportionable vilanies: let him thinke there is no divill in hell, no Pope at Rome, no malice in the heart of a Ieſuite.</p>
            <p>Me thinks, it is an aſtoniſhment beyond the comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of nature, reaſon, religion, policies of State: that ſuch an intollerable generation, ſo odious both to heaven and earth, with abominable Idolatry; ſo viſibly infamous, both to this and the other world, with many capitall cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of blood; ſo endleſſe and implacable, in their rage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſignments, againſt the crowned Majeſty of the Kings Throne; ſo prodigious in their plots, that they have caſt an inexpiable and everlaſting aſperſion, upon the innocency of Chriſtian Religion; ſuch furious Aſſaſins and Incendia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for murthering or Princes, butchery of people and e, firing of States; ſo inraged, even like Wolves in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening, to ſwallow us up quicke (if the time did ſerve;) I ſay, that ſuch, in ſo orthodoxe a Church, and noble a State, ſhould by allowance, toleration, connivencie, or remiſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and paraliticall diſtempet of the arme of Iuſtice, or ſome thing, be ſuffered to receive encreaſement, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, both in number, and inſolency, to the great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour of God Almighty, the continuall vexation of Gods people and good Subjects, and the moſt certaine hazard of the whole State, and the peacefull ſucceſſion of the Kings poſterity. It would never be, but that the Lord in his juſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, intends, &amp; prepares us for ſome dreadfull judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And I am afraid, Papiſts will be the men, to execute
<pb facs="tcp:112876:7"/>Gods heavie wrath upon us: becauſe they are a principall matter in the meane time, of high offence againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty.</p>
            <p>To let paſſe infinite more of very ſpeciall, and materiall ponderations, to this purpoſe; conſider, I pray you, but this one point, with feeling apprehendſions, which is able to inflame the heart of an ingenuous Heathen with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary indignation. I am perſwaded, there was not a Papiſt in this land, whatſoever may be pretended, or proteſted to the contrary, but did heartily rejoyce, at the taking away of that thrice, nay thouſand times noble and bleſſed Prince,<note place="margin">P. H.</note> of ſweeteſt memory, for which the heart of every true Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, did ſhead moſt worthily, even teares of blood. Now, what a rufull caſe is this, that ſuch vipers ſhould bemouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the bowels and boſome of this Kingdome; the breath, heart, and life whereof, they hartyly wiſh, and would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce to have extinguiſhed? To conclude the whole point for the preſent: it is the generall joynt conſent, and current concluſion of all the Chriſtian orthodox reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches upon the face of Europe; and it is worthyly, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerably demonſtrated by our gracious Soveraigne, that the Pope is Antichriſt; and Rome, myſticall Babylon.<note place="margin">K. I.</note> Some particular men, (out of curioſity and conceit of their owne wit, affectation of ſingularity, doting addiction to popiſh writers, want of further illumination in the point, partiall inclinations towards the divinity of Rome, or the like) may diſſent, without prejudice of a truth, ſo univerſally reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved upon, by Divines of beſt learning, and ſincereſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If ſo; then tell me the meaning of ſuch places as theſe, and to whom the ſpirit of God directs the edge and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</p>
            <p>Reward her even as ſhee hath rewarded you, and give her double, according to her workes: and in the cup that ſhee hath filled you, fill her the double; <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:112876:8"/>
            <p>And the ten hornes, which thou ſaweſt upon the beaſt, are they that ſhall hate the whore, and ſhall make her deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and naked, and ſhall eate her fleſh, and burne her with fire, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.16. This prediction by the judgement of the beſt divines, hath the power, and paſſeth into the nature of a precept, and therefore is charged as a commandement, upon thoſe of whom it is ſpoken.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and the like, doe indeed ſtrongly confirme, and make good thoſe three propoſitions of that learned man, and excellent light of
<hi>Heildelberge,</hi> in his booke <hi>de iure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum,</hi> pag. 6. <hi>&amp; ſequ.</hi> The ſumme whereof may bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived into this concluſion; Princes and Magiſtrates, with their ſwords and ſcepters; Preachers, by the word and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; private men, by Prayer, and all lawfull oppoſition, ought to doe their their beſt and utmoſt, to bring confuſion upon that
<hi>man of ſinne,</hi> and his accurſed doctrine. And thus to follow the councell of the bleſſed Spirit, in rooting out the limbes of Antichriſt, and Antichriſtianiſme, is ſo farre from being perſecution, that it is a very glorious ſervice unto the Majeſty of the God of heaven. The neglect where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and impunity of Idolatry is able in ſhort time, to ſhake the pillers, and diſtrengthen the ſinewes, to decrowne the head, and ſhorten the raigne of the ſtrongeſt State, and moſt potent Prince in the world Delayes are dangerous; Policy to the contrary is pernicious; and counivency, cruelty; in ſuch places where theſe ſayings have place <hi>bleſſed ſhall he be, that taketh and daſheth her children againſt the ſtones,</hi> Pſal. 137.9. <hi>All yee that bend the bow, ſhoot at her, ſpare no arrowes: for ſhe hath ſinned against the Lord, Ier.</hi> 50.14.
<hi>In as much as ſhe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied her ſelfe, and lived in pleaſure, ſo much give you to her, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſorrow,</hi> Revel. 18.7.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, vntill the holy Spirits counſell and commandement to this purpoſe, be taken to heart, and <pb facs="tcp:112876:8"/>throughly put in execution, I pray the Lord to ſtay their rageful malice, and to turne their popiſh murtherous hearts for whetting any more ſwords, to ſhead the blood of the Lords annoynted: or elſe, to turne the ſharpeſt ſwords from the point, with a cutting edge on both ſides, even up to the very hilts, in their owne hearts blood. And in deſpite of hell and Rome, good Lord, wee pray thee, let King <hi>Charles</hi> flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſtill, with a crowne of glory on his head, and a ſcepter of triumph in his hand, and ſtill waſh his Princely feet in the blood of his enemies.</p>
            <p>Thus much I thought good to Epiſtle at this time, for the diſcharge of my owne conſcience, and the needfull refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your memories, with the apprehenſion of thoſe dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dangers, which howerly hang over our heads, by reaſon of the impunity of Popiſh Idolatry, and the endleſſe inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table malice and machinations of the Papiſts. We have had provocations, and warnings enough; from this place, from the Parliament houſe: from heaven, by Gods meſſengers; from hell by the powder-plot, from <hi>Ireland</hi> by their heathen Tyranny from Rome, by the roring of their Buls; from <hi>France,</hi> by their maſſacres, and butchery of their Kings: by more mediate, and politicke; by immediate and miraculous revelations, diſcoveries, deliverances: by a blacke and bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy catalogue of moſt hatefull and prodigious conſpiracies, which runne parallell with the golden fine of Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeths</hi> life; by the dayly villanous libels of the ſwaggering runagates of our countrey; baſe and illiterate pamphlets, ſtuft with ribaldrie, and railings, and perſonall ſlanders, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencies, out-facings, utterly without any paſſage or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of grace, or gracious ſpirit. A thouſand times, a thouſand wayes; And yet what good have they done, ſith nothing will ſerve the turne? Gods will muſt bee done. For mine owne part, I have delivered mine owne ſoule. If any
<pb facs="tcp:112876:9"/>will not take warning, whom it concernes, his blood be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his owne head.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed is he, who forc-ſees the ſtorme, and hide him ſelfe in the meane time, vnder the winges of Chriſt, and ſhelter of a good conſcience. With which Concluſion as hee ended, I alſo conclude, commending this pithie ſpeech of my ſo learned afreind, to your wiſedome and godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, your ſelves to Gods holy protection, and all your iuſt proceedings to his gracious bleſſing, that you may confidently look for a reward of your well doing in the end of your dayes.</p>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:112876:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
